Finding Aid for the Brian Urquhart Collection of Material about Ralph Bunche, ca. 1932-1972
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Biographical Notes, Early Life, Family., [Box 39, 8 folders]
  - Biographical accounts. (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Original reprint of R.J. Bunche's My Most Unforgettable Character., 1969. (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - R.J. Bunche: from Intellectual to Icon B. Keppel CAAS., 1992. (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - The Reporter: R.J. Bunche-Statesman., 1949. (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Collier's: R.J. Bunche: American Peacemaker R.B. Gehman., June 11, 1949. (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Letter: R.J. Bunche-Etta Gordon., January 19, 1935. (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Original Reader's Digest Unforgettable R.J. Bunche by L.B. Pearson., March 1973. (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - B.E. Urquhart's tribute, and remembrances Los Angeles Times., May 15, 1975. (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - R.J. Bunche Personal Life. (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - R.J. Bunche's anecdotes. (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - The Man Who Stops Fights by H.E. & K.Pringle. Saturday Evening Post., August 13, 1949. (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - Publisher's Typescript of blurb about P.Mann's book R.J. Bunche: UN Peacemaker, E.M. Riley-R.J. Bunche., January 25, 1956.; Typescript (carbon) (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - Image-makers script for R.J. Bunche by W. Rydell. (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - R.J. Bunche's Champion of Colonial Peoples., 1953. (Box 39, Folder 8)
- Family Letters (Johnson Family and Miscellaneous Family Correspondence Unrestricted)., [Box 40, 4 folders]
  - Family letters: Nelle, Ethel, Jane Taylor, etc. (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Handwritten Letters: R.J. Bunche to: Ruth-Nelle (); R.J. Bunche-Ethel (); original R.J. Bunche-Joan ()., December 28, 1931 September 28 March 24, 1957. (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Transcribed letters of Ethel & Nelle:., June 14, 1949-September 3, 1974, August 2, 1935-March 4, 1949. (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Letters - Johnson. (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Transcribed Johnson letters., June 14, 1949-September 3, 1974. (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Nelle, Ethel, Jane. (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Transcripts of letters., December 3, 1928-September 3, 1974. (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Interview with Jane Taylor., August 21, 1989. (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - R.J. Bunche - Joan correspondence. (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - Handwritten letter to Joan from R.J. Bunche., January 31, 1952. (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Bulk., Ca. 1957-1967, 1988. (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Original letter: Ruth-G.L. Zeckendorf (); Christmas card from Countess Bernadotte ()., January 29, 1988 late 1950s. (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Letters: T.Lie, Nobel Prize Committee, 10 Best Groomed Men Committee., February 7, 1961.; Typescript (carbon) (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Congressional Record., January 15, 1962. (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Congressional Record., April 3, 24, 25-May 15, 1962. (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Letters:. (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - re Bang-Jensen., 1966. (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - re anti-UN propaganda., 1967. (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Secretary General-R.J. Bunche Confidential., August 23, 1966.; Typescript (carbon) (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Secretary General statement., November 1, 1966. (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Report re resolution 227., Typescript (carbon) (Box 40, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous Letters, Notes, Memos, (Includes Legal Letters Related to Ralph J. Bunche)., 1954-1994.; [Box 40, 1 folder]
  - Letters re R.J. Bunche papers; R.J. Bunche estate; investments; medical; savings account; Ruth in Board of Directors of City University New York (); UN bylaws; UCLA library ()., 1971-75 January 17, 1974 1975.; (Originals) (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Los Angeles Times: B.E. Urquhart's Remembrances of R.J. Bunche., May 15, 1975. (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Ruth's will () Typescript (carbon); statement of Attending Physician (); Dividend Shares (); R.J. Bunche's assets (); life insurance (); investment program ()., 1972 December 9, 1971 1973 March 20, 1972 1972 1972. (Box 40, Folder 6)
- Brian E. Urquhart's Notes of Tapes for Bunche Biography., [Boxes 40-43, 20 folders]
  - Transcript of B.E. Urquhart's Tapes., 1945-1960s. (Box 40-42)
    General note
    (Tapes 15-22 missing)
    - Transcript of Tapes 1 through 7., 1945-1948.; (pp.1-454) (Box 40, Folder 7)
      With annotations.
    - Transcript of Tapes 8 through 14., 1948-1949.; (pp.440-853) (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Transcript of Tape 1., 1946-1947. (Box 41, Folder 2)
      Side 1: R.J. Bunche's attendance at 1st session of UN General Assembly, December 30, 1945-February 16, 1946.
      Side 2: R.J. Bunche's activities up to November 1947.
    - Transcript of Tape 2., 1930-1947. (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Transcript of Tape 3., 1932-1945. (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Transcript of Tape 4., 1914-1971. (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Transcript of Tape 5., 1914-1947. (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Transcript of Tape 6., 1914-1947. (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Transcript of Tape 7., 1948: January-June. (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Transcript of Tape 8., 1948. (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Transcript of Tape 10., 1948: January-June. (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Transcript of Tape 9., 1948: January-June. (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Transcript of Tape 11., 1947-1948. (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Transcript of Tape 12., 1948: July-August. (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Transcript of Tape 13., 1948: June. (Box 42, Folder 3)
      re random quotations mostly about proposals that Bernadotte made on the 27th of June, 1948.
    - Transcript of tape 14., 1948: September. (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Transcript of Tapes 23-28., 1950-1963. (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Transcript of Tapes 27-35., 1956-1968.; (pp.10453-1364) (Box 42, Folder 6)
      With annotations. Some pages missing and misplaced.
    - Incomplete Tapes 36-46., 1960-1966.; (pp.1365-1763) (Box 42, Folder 7)
      Incomplete, with annotations and missing pages.
    - Incomplete tapes 48 and 50-54., 1960s.; (pp.981-2053) (Box 43, Folder 1)
      Incomplete and in no particular order.
- Tapes of Ralph Bunche Conference, City University, Graduate Center, Ralph J. Bunche Institute., [Boxes 43-44, 9 folders]
  - [Untitled]., n.d.; (Cassette) (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - [Urquhart Session, Sides A, B]., n.d.; (Cassette) (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - [R.J. Bunche re Decolonization 2, Discussants]., n.d.; (Cassette) (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - [Closing session]., n.d.; (Cassette) (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - [Urquhart Session - Panel 6]., n.d.; (Cassette) (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - [R.J. Bunche's Impact on American Perception of Africa - Martin Kilson Panel 3]., n.d. (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - [3/6 - Hertzberg]., n.d.; (Cassette) (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - [R.J. Bunche as UN Mediator - Panel V - J.C. Hurewitz]., n.d.; (Cassette) (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - [The Development of a Black Africanist -Nathan Higgins. R.J. Bunche: Political Scientist and Teacher at Howard -Vincent Brown Panel 1]., (Cassette) (Box 44, Folder 4)
- Interviews (for Brian E. Urquhart's Ralph J. Bunche Biography)., [Box 44, 2 folders]
  - [Comments on R.J. Bunche by interviewers]., 1982, 1986, 1988, 1992. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Original letter: B.E. Urquhart-T.M. Hesburgh., June 25, 1992. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Ralph Bunche Conference., May-June 1986. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Notes on Trusteeship Council., 1946-1950. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - William Mashler interview., September 24, 1986, January 27, 1988, March 16, 1982. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Jane Taylor interview. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Questions for Reedman. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Interview, James Green., May and December 1982. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Memo B.E. Urquhart-B. Nelson., January 22, 1982. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Interview, Kenneth Dadzie., January 20, 1982. (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Interviews: Shivashinka (March 12, 1982), General Rikhye, Ingrid Nagorski, General Preuchand (August 19, 1982). (Box 44, Folder 5)
      Also, K. Clark transcript.
  - [Interviews]., 1981-1983, 1988-1989. (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Summary of main ideas of R.J. Bunche's dissertation. (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Interviews: L. Flemming (); James Green (); Cleanthro de Paiva Leite (); J. Liu (); W. Mashler; J. Reedman (); I. Negorski., April 28, 1983 May and December 1982 September 20, 1989 December 15, 1981 June 20, 1988. (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Interviews: L. General Preuchand (); General Rikhye; Shivashinka ()., August 19, 1982 March 12, 1982. (Box 44, Folder 6)
- Appointment Diaries., 1967-1970.; [Boxes 44 and 46, 4 folders]
  - ., 1968: January-May.; (Photocopy) (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - ., 1968: June-December.; (Photocopy) (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - ., 1969.; (Photocopy) (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - ., 1970.; (Photocopy) (Box 46, Folder 2)
- Correspondence re Disposition of Ralph J. Bunche Material (UCLA, Schomburg, and other Institutions)., [Box 46, 3 folders]
  - Glenn Horowitz Bookseller appraisal of R.J. Bunche archive., July 18, 1991. (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Papers re Schomburg receipt of R.J. Bunche collection 1991. (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Harmer Johnson re Ruth Bunche Estate 1989. (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - First of two appraisals of Ralph Bunche Family Archives., June 25, 1990. (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Letters, some originals, re UCLA as repository of R.J. Bunche papers (); declassifacation of restricted materials especially UN related (); B. Nelson's visit to UCLA ()., 1973 1973-77, 1982 1982, 1985. (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Letters, some original, re B.E. Urquhart & classification of R.J. Bunche papers at UCLA (); Trachtenberg's observations of R.J. Bunche papers ()., 1976 1978. (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - UN staff regulation 1.5 re R.J. Bunche's UN files., January 26, 1971. (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Letters, some original, re Joan on segregation; R.J. Bunche papers, memorabilia, & personal effects (); R.J. Bunche House as monument ()., 1989 June 17, 1976. (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Detroit History Museum list. (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Letters, some original, re publication of R.J. Bunche's S. Voting Behavior manuscript (); other institutions' offers to house R.J. Bunche papers (); Smithsonian Institution donations (); Negro History Association ()., 1972 1972 1972 1967, 1972. (Box 46, Folder 5)
- Various Listings, Indices of Ralph J. Bunche Papers (Ford Foundation, Schomburg)., [Box 46-47, 4 folders]
  - Ford Foundation Transmittal and Receipt Forms from the International Affairs Program re Ralph Bunche papers., December 20, 1989. (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - Master Index I: Meetings w/Secretary General. (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Master Index 2 - General documentation on: Near East, Vietnam, Congo, Cyprus, Dominican Republic, Indo-Pakistan, Cambodia-Thailand. (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Master Index 3: Miscellaneous categories/ General documentation. (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Indices compiled by Joan Bunche & Susanna Spalding & given to UN archives. (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - [Boxes in Ford Foundation to be transferred to UN Archives]. (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Ford Foundation Transmittal and Receipt Forms, duplicate copies., December 20, 1989. (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - [Schomburg]. (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - Description of Ralph Bunche papers by Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture at New York Public Library., 1991. (Box 47, Folder 2)
- Listings of Ralph J. Bunche Files (UN Archives)., [Box 47, 3 folders]
  - [Listing no.1]. (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - Listing of material belonging to R.J. Bunche which was housed in boxes in the UN archives., 1933-1971. (Box 47, Folder 3)
      This material was eventually donated to the Schomburg.
  - [Listing no.2]. (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Listing of material belonging to R.J. Bunche which was housed in boxes in the UN archives., 1929-1971. (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - UN Archives Records Transmittal & Receipt forms., March 2, 1987. (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - United Nations Truce Supervision Organization Headquarters - Maps., 1967, 1971. (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - List: Middle East papers., 1967-68. (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - List: Secretary General papers., 1961-1971. (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Archive lists for Secretary General and R.J. Bunche., 1947-1970. (Box 47, Folder 5)
- Listing of U Thant's Files., 1961-1971.; [Box 48, 1 folder]
  - UN memo () re descriptive inventory to U Thant's papers for Secretary General office., August 12, 1980 1961-1971. (Box 48, Folder 1)
- Bibliography for Bunche Biography, Including Excerpts from Books and other Miscellaneous Books., [Boxes 48-50, 18 folders]
  - Partial bibliography list. (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Finkelstein chapter: Trusteeship vs. Self-Determination. (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Journal: Commentary (vol.56 no.6)., December 1973. (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Chapters 1, 2, & 5 of Race & Radicalism by Wilson Record. (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - The National Negro Congress from The Crisis of the Negro Intellectual by Harold Cruse., 1967. (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - A UN Peacekeeping Force for the Gulf? by A. James. (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - An American Dilemma: The Negro Problem and Modern Democracy by Gunnar Myrdal. (Box 48, Folder 4)
    Selected chapters.
  - Black Americans in the Roosevelt Era by John B. Kirby., n.d. (Box 48, Folder 5)
    The preface and selected chapters.
  - Gunnar Myrdal and Black-White Relations by David W. South. (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Letter: H.J. Gates Jr. - Joan. H. Bunche., June 11, 1991. (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Excerpts from various publications re economics/race/class & international parallels/Africa., 1936, 1959, 1960, 1963, 1968, 1969. (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Excerpts from David W. Southern's Gunnar Myrdal and Black-White Relations: The Use and Abuse of An American Dilemma 1944-1969., October 8, 1987. (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Selected chapters from Walter A. Jackson's Gunnar Myrdal and America's Conscience: Social Engineering and Racial Liberalism, 1938-1987. (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Dissertation: Castles in Spain: United States Trusteeship Plans in World War II by L.S. Finkelstein., 1970. (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Book: The 1965-66 Jennings Scholar Lectures., 1965-1966. (Box 49, Folder 2)
    Includes R.J. Bunche on the UN, January 8, 1966.
  - Book: State in the Making by David Horowitz., 1953. (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Paperback book: The Peace Prize by August Schou., 1962. (Box 49, Folder 4)
    Signed to R.J. Bunche December 18, 1962 & reprinted from Nobel: The Man and His Prizes.
  - Book: Present at the Creation: My Years in the State Department by Dean Acheson., 1969. (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Book: Peace in Their Time: Men Who Led Us In and Out of War, 1914-1945 by Emery Kelen., 1963. (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Book: Incidents and Coincidences: Adventures in Foreign Affairs by Irving Salomon., 1980. (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - Book: Kennedy by Theodore C. Sorensen (Special Counsel to the Late President)., 1965. (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - Book: As It Was: An inside view of Politics and Power in the 1950s and 1960s by Henry Cabot Lodge., 1976. (Box 50, Folder 1)
    Signed by the author to Ruth Bunche.
  - Book: Golda: The Life of Israel's Prime Minister by Peggy Mann., 1971. (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - Book: Crisis: The Inside Story of the Suez Conspiracy by Terence Robertson., 1965. (Box 50, Folder 3)
- FBI Files: Ralph Bunche., 1940-1967, 1984, 1995.; [Boxes 36 and 45, 16 folders]
  - FBI Files: Ralph Bunche., 1940-1967, 1984, 1995. (Box 45, Folder 1-10, Box 36, Folder 1-6)